I want to talk about storing things.
We've talked about variables.
Now, we mentioned that variables are like storage places where you put things.
But when you think about it, you actually have different places where you store different things.
So, you know, we might see some of these things in a big container like that that stores boxes, or
I suppose you could store a car in there, but you wouldn't store your frozen turkey for Thanksgiving
in here, would you?
And I'm assuming unless you have a huge, huge supply of shoes, you probably wouldn't use a store your
shoes and that would go in your cupboard and on and goes.
If you've got books, you're going to store books, maybe in some sort of bookcase.
So the point is we store different things in different spaces.
Cars go into garages.
Food goes into fridges.
Knives and forks go into drawers and on and on it goes.
So it's important when we come to our programming that we realize that different spaces store different
things.
And so our variables are actually different types and they are called data types.
So when we come to variables, not all variables are the same.
So we started and we looked at the one variable which was a greeting or a name.
And we had something we stored in it.
But we actually need to understand that you get different types of variables.
And it's important that we understand that a little bit.
There are a couple of different types of variables, but we're going to focus on the most important
and the most basic variables that Python has.
So you can see here there are a list of the different data types.
And we're actually going to cover most of these.
But to start off with I'm going to look at the top three.
So firstly I'm going to look at strings because you actually already know what strings are.
So if we go back to our program.
You'll see.
Remember when I told you if you're writing something that is text, put it inside quotation marks.
So this actually creates something called a string.
So basically anything that you put inside quotation marks is a string.
So and the thing with strings is it's totally ignored.
Whatever you put in there.
You can put in whatever you can put in special, uh symbols if you like.
You can put in just about anything.
That's the thing with a string.
A string doesn't care what is in there.
So you can go crazy inside here.
You can even store just a number inside quotation marks.
But this is now no longer a number.
It's seen as a string or text.
Okay, that's very important because we'll look at a different type of different data type that that
allows you to store numbers.
So if you wanted to do calculations, you wouldn't store your number as a string because it won't see
it as a number then.
Okay.
So you can already see here another data type is numbers, so numbers can be split up into a couple
different subcategories.
The most important ones that you really need to know are integers and floats.
So you can see here basically if you try and figure it out you can easily see an integer is something
that has no decimal.
So basically it's just a one with no point.
It's a whole number five seven, three and a decimal can.
Now again you know often you don't need the the decimal point.
So maybe you're doing a counter.
How many squirrels in my garden.
123.
Again, unless you've done something to one of the squirrels you shouldn't have 1.1 squirrels.
But if you're doing a calculation, you know, what are the average number of squirrels in my garden?
Obviously.
Now maybe you want to get the average number is 3.2.
So that's when you would decide whether you are using an integer or not.
Okay.
So Python's pretty clever and it almost automatically will figure out what data type you're trying to
use.
So if I now type my number as my variable name and I want to equal it.
I want to assign it to a number value.
I can assign it to whatever I want.
Let's just say I want to go 38.
I've now created a variable called my number, which is storing a data type called an integer instead
of before where we had a storing a string.
Now, if we wanted to print this and we wanted to print my number.
You're going to see it just prints 38 and I don't I'm sure you can guess if I now put string.
Uh, if I put quotation marks around this 38, it actually prints exactly the same thing.
So printing just a value, it's just showing you the contents of the number.
It's not actually doing anything with it.
But we'll see in a moment that if it's not an integer, you're going to have a problem.
So now where this becomes important is when you want to add things or subtract things, which we'll
actually look at in more detail later on.
But for now you just need to know.
If you want to type an integer, just type it in.
And if I wanted to now make it a float, I can just put the decimal place and it's now going to.
This is now called a float okay.
So the last data type we're going to look at is a data type called booleans.
Booleans are basically a fancy word for true or false.
Yeah this is a cool thing about learning to program because you can impress your friends and family.
Now try this.
This thing.
I promise you, this work.
You're going to serve dinner tonight.
Hopefully you still have dinner around the table, and you're sitting around the table and just all
chatting, chatting, and then just say, oh, sorry, can you pass me the boolean?
Oh, I meant the salt.
And your whole family is going to look at you and go, man, what did you you're so clever.
And I promise you, from there on out, they're just going to think you are the person.
So impress them with the big words, big word for you to impress them with this boolean.
So what's it what's boolean.
Yeah.
Well actually back on that I actually remember in my first ever lecture on programming, my lecturer
told me that Programmers love to use confusing words for simpler things to make everyone else think
that you are talking about something that's really complicated and that obviously.
So that's basically what programming is.
If you just learn the more confusing words, you actually are learning things that you already know.
But just.
Yeah.
So they're just fancy words for things fancy.
Yeah, exactly.
That's why we're trying to make this accessible to everyone.
We know that anyone can do this if you just put your mind to it.
So back onto booleans.
True or false.
So now let's type a boolean variable.
Yeah.
Because one number wouldn't make sense to be a boolean okay.
People often just shorten boolean to bool okay.
So like I said before this can only be the value true or false.
I cannot type anything else into boolean value.
As soon as I type something that does not say true or false, it's no longer a boolean value.
So this doesn't really do anything very exciting, but you'll see why they are so important later on.
It's just going to print the value.
True.
But if I change this to true one, it's now going to complain because it thinks this is a string, but
we haven't got quotation marks around it.
Yes.
And also as you see at the bottom here, it actually thinks that this is the name of a variable.
So down the bottom you'll notice it's undefined.
It's saying true.
One is not defined because it's assuming this must be a variable, something that you've stored something
in elsewhere.
But I can't find it.
Obviously if you did this and you put inverted commas around it, well obviously now even though it's
called marble, this is actually just a string that you've created.
So you actually haven't created a boolean at all.
And so that's why it's important.
Even if you did that remember that's still not going to be a boolean.
It's a string.
So booleans are simply, as Sarah said true or false.
And you can see it change color as well, telling you that this is a reserved word in Python.
Okay.
So then obviously you can also use false.
Another thing just make sure that you are doing is this has to for boolean values the first letter has
to be a capital.
So it's true with a capital T or false with a capital F.
Otherwise it again doesn't recognize it.
Make sure that it is the correct color.
Now these are some of the silly things with these programming languages.
They get a bit irritating, but you get used to it.
We mentioned earlier that you don't start your variables with a capital, but you can, as you see here,
have a capital letter inside your variable name.
It sometimes helps to try and make it easier to read.
So you might have my name, or my string or my bool.
And so you've got here we've got a big B.
So that's okay.
So small letters at the start.
But when you're assigning a boolean value it must be a capital F or T okay.
So those are the three most important data types that we will need for now.
And already you know a lot more about variables.
You can see there are a couple more.
We will look at some of these later.
But these are all you need for now.